Emile Cyrus Houle Collection 1896-2010 (bulk 1910-1927)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Emile Cyrus Houle Collection 1896-2010, (bulk 1910-1927)
MS 478
Houle, Emile Cyrus
Photographs, scrapbooks, and printed materials, 1896-2010 (bulk 1910-1927). This collection is comprised of photo albums, scrapbooks, loose photographs, and printed materials documenting the life and travels of Emile Cyrus Houle. The bulk of the material relates to his medical career as a surgeon for the S. P. de Mexico Railroad Company and USA Medical Corps in France during WWI, and archaeological excavations undertaken in Mexico and the American southwest. Topics of interest include the Mexican Revolution, WWI, and medical research and publications on a number of topics including yellow fever on the northwest coast of Mexico in the early-mid 1920s.
7.75 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
There are no restrictions on this collection.
Biographical Note
Emile Cyrus Houle was born June 5th, 1881 in Michigamme, Michigan and graduated, M. D., from the University of Michigan in 1904. Following brief stays at the Tamarack Hospital in Calumet, Michigan and the Mohak and Wolverine mines in Kearsarge, Michigan as Assistant Surgeon from 1904-1905 and 1905-1907 respectively, Houle became the Assistant Surgeon of the Sud Pacifico (S. P.) de Mexico Railroad Company on the west coast of Mexico in 1907 where he worked under George Emory Goodfellow, M. D. Over the next 10 years, Houle advanced from Assistant Surgeon to Chief Surgeon of the S. P. de Mexico Railroad Company before enlisting in the U. S. A. Medical Corps in 1917 for the WWI war effort. His military service included service in the 1st Battalion 20th Engineers, Dax, France and the Surgeon Camp, Dax, France, and a commission to Major, M. C., before discharge after 13 months of service in 1919. After his military service, Houle returned as Chief Surgeon of the S. P. de Mexico Railroad Company in 1919 where he stayed before resigning in 1926. His medical career continued as a general practitioner in his home, Nogales, until the 1950s. During his medical career, Houle contributed to and wrote a number of published research articles on a variety of topics, including yellow fever on the Mexican west coast from 1921-1925, and is credited with aiding in the eradication of malaria in Sonora, Mexico.
Houle was married to Loretta Fitzpatrick Houle and had two sons, Alan and Peter. Apart from his medical career, Houle was also an amateur archaeologist, his excavations having resulted in a collection of pre-Columbian statues which have since been donated to a state museum, many photographs documenting his finds, and a written narrative of his travels. His time with the S. P. de Mexico Railroad Company also offered Houle a unique perspective of the Mexican Revolution as it proceeded in Empalme, Sonora Mexico. This perspective is reflected in research gathered in conjunction with the superintendent of the railway and friend, Victor W. Bennett.
Emile Cyrus Houle passed away October 21st, 1966.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into 5 series.
Series I: Archaeological Scrapbooks circa 1910-1950s
Series II: Photographs 1902-1920, 1927-1931
Subseries 1: Photo Albums
Subseries 2: Loose Photos
Series III: Printed Materials 1907-1971, 2008-2010
Series IV: Genealogy 1896-1982
Series V: Oversize Materials 1904-1948
Scope and Content Note
Photographs, scrapbooks, and printed materials, 1896-2010 (bulk 1910-1927). This collection is comprised of photo albums, scrapbooks, loose photographs, and printed materials documenting the life and travels of Emile Cyrus Houle. The bulk of the material relates to his medical career as a surgeon for the S. P. de Mexico Railroad Company and USA Medical Corps in France during WWI, and archaeological excavations undertaken in Mexico and the American southwest. Working as a surgeon for the S. P. de Mexico Railroad Company on the west coast of Mexico from 1907-1920’s, Houle was present for events related to the Mexican Revolution, which are documented in photographs, journal entries, and research printed materials in the collection. Well represented events include the Banquet Massacre of Yaqui Chiefs and the Imuris Incident. His medical career also included 13 months of service in the U.S.A. Medical Corps in France during WWI from 1917-1919 with promotion to Major, M. C., U.S.A, which is documented primarily in correspondences, journal entries, and other documents.
Houle’s time in Mexico and the American southwest also allowed for a career as an amateur archaeologist with excavations in Ixtlán del Río, Mazatlán, and Tepic, Mexico, and Nogales and Tuba City, AZ, among other locations. These archaeological excavations are greatly represented in two scrapbooks and loose items of mainly photographic material depicting sculpture figurines and rock art. The two scrapbooks include copies of a potential future publication documenting Houle archaeological career, with the inclusion of notes, rough drafts, and final versions of a five chapter personal narrative describing it. The narrative can be found in the printed materials. Apart from his professional careers, his personal life is represented in early photographs starting from 1902 and correspondences and photographs from later in life mainly during the 1950s and 1960s.
Access Terms
Goodfellow, George Emory, 1855-1910
Ixtlán del Río (Nayarit, Mexico) -- Antiquities
Mexico -- Antiquities
Mexico -- History -- Revolution, 1910-1920
Railroads -- Mexico
World War, 1914-1918
Yellow fever -- Mexico
Photographs
Container List
- Series I: Archaeological Scrapbooks circa 1910-1960s
  This series contains two scrapbooks document Emile Cyrus Houle’s archaeological findings and travels. They contain photographs and descriptions of pre-Columbian archaeological finds, including statuettes, figurines, rock art, pottery, and other ceramics from locations such as Manzanillo, Guaymas, and Ixtlán del Río along the west coast of Mexico. These scrapbooks may have been layouts for intended publications and thus loose items have been documented by the pages they were originally found on or between. Scrapbook 1 is more complete than Scrapbook 2.
  - Scrapbook 1, circa 1910-1950s (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook 2, circa 1910-1960s (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook 1 - Loose Items by Page, Cover – p. 83, circa 1910-1950s (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook 1 – Loose Items by Page, p. 84 – 127, circa 1910-1950s (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook 2 – Loose Cover Items – Maps and Other, circa 1910-1960s (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook 2 – Loose Cover Items – Notes, circa 1910-1960s (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook 2 – Loose Cover Items – Photographs and Negatives, circa 1910-1960s (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook 2 – Loose Items by Page circa 1910-1960s (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Series II: Photographs, circa 1900-1960s
  This series contains photographic material including photo albums and loose photographs found in the collection.
  - Subseries 1:Photo Albums
    - Photo Album Digital Scans (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Photo Album 1 – Loose Items, 1902-1907 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Photo Album 2 – Loose Items, 1907-1910 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Photo Album 3 – Loose Items, 1910-1917 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Photo Album 4 – Loose Items, 1915-1920, 1928, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Photo Album 5 – Loose Items, 1916, 1920-1927 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Photo Album 1, 1902-1907 (Box 4)
    - Photo Album 2, 1907-1910 (Box 5)
    - Photo Album 3, 1910-1917 (Box 6)
    - Photo Album 4, 1915-1920, 1928, 1931 (Box 7)
    - Photo Album 5, 1916, 1920-1927 (Box 8)
  - Subseries 2: Loose Photographs
    - Archaeology and Anthropology, circa 1912-1957, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Archaeology and Anthropology, circa 1920s-1957, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Arizona, circa 1940s, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Family and Friends, circa 1910-1940s (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Family and Friends, circa 1950s-1960s, undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Houle Gate Nogales, 1940, 1950-1954, 1961 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Island of San Torin, 1956 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Mexico, circa 1910-1957, undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - US, 1919, 1940s, undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Unknown Location, 1915, 1940, undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Unknown People, 1925, 1937, undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
- Series III: Printed Materials, 1907-1971, 2008-2010
  This series contains printed materials from Houle’s professional and personal lives including correspondences, journal entries, and research files. Materials of interest include journal entries during his military service in WWI, a five chapter narrative of his archaeological travels and excavations, and research regarding the Mexican Revolution and yellow fever on the Mexican west coast in the 1920s.
  - Archaeology and Anthropology circa 1950s, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Archaeology Narrative, undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Certificates, 1919-1925, 1936, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Correspondences, 1907-1937, 1947-1966, undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Correspondences – Family and Friends, 1932-1935, 1953-1959 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Correspondences – Family and Friends, 1960-1971, 2008-2010, undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Correspondences – Victor W. Bennett, 1953-1956 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Correspondences – Victor W. Bennett, 1957-1962 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Correspondences – Victor W. Bennett, undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Correspondences – George Goodfellow, M. D., 1908-1910 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Deeds, 1937 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Houle Biography, circa 1920s, 1960, undated (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Houle Dayplanners, 1953, 1956 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Journals Spring 1907-Nov. 1917, May 1919-Jan. 1922 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Journals – WWI, Nov. 1917-May 1919 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings circa 1940-1960s, undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Research, circa 1920s, 1950s, undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Research – Biographies, circa 1920s, 1940s, undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Research – George Goodfellow, M. D., 1932, circa 1950-1960s, undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Index Cards, A-W (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Research – Medical 1925, 1944, 1964, undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Research – Medical – “The Balmis Expedition For Control of Smallpox by Vaccination”, circa 1930s, undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Research – Medical – “Belated Serum Treatment of Sequelae of Diphtheria”, 1933 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Research – Medical – “Bone Metabolism in Relation to Industrial Surgery”, circa 1930s, undated (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Research – Medical – “Calcium in Therapeutics” 1935, undated (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Research – Medical – “Evaluation of Factors in Bone Union” 1938, undated (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Research – Medical – “Metabolism in Relation to Fractures” circa 1930s, undated (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Research – Medical – “Yellow Fever – West Coast 1921-1925” 1923-1925, 1930 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Research – Mexican Revolution 1913-1915, 1921, undated (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Research – Mexican Revolution – Banquet Massacre of Yaqui Chiefs 1921, 1953, 1957 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Research – Mexican Revolution – Imuris Incident circa 1910-1920s, 1950s, undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Research – Poetry, Songs, and Stories 1909, 1958, 1961, undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Sketches 1914, undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
- Series IV: Genealogy 1896-1982
  This series contains materials of various formats as they were collected by Houle and later descendants in order to document their genealogy. Formats include photographs and printed materials, including correspondences, family histories, maps, newspaper clippings, and notes.
  - Albert J. Houle 1896-1917, 1964, undated (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Alice Houle (Alice Sturgeon) 1950, undated (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Arthur Houle 1912, 1923-1962, undated (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Borbeau Family 1954-1958, undated (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Eugene Houle 1949-1965, undated (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Louise Exilia and Cyrille Houle III 1900, 1925-1927, undated (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Fitzpatrick Family 1913-1938, 1955-1963, undated (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Fitzpatrick Family undated (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Fred Houle 1905, 1943-1965, undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - George Houle 1918, 1926, undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Josephine Houle (Josephine Hanna) 1941-1964, 1978-1982, undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Louis Houle 1924, 1957-1959, undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings with People Named Houle undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
- Series V: Oversize Materials 1904-1948
  This series contains oversized materials, including degrees, certificates, photographs, maps, and other printed materials.
  - Oversize Materials 1904-1948, undated (Box 14)